{"tossups": [{"question": "The Soviet-built Salang Tunnel in this mountain range connects Tokharistan [toe-CAR-ee-stan] with points south, shortcutting the Shibar (SHY-bar) Pass. Tirich Mir [TEE-rich meer] is the highest point of this range, which is home to the Kokcha [COKE-cha] Valley\u2019s ancient mines  of spinels and lapis lazuli. The massacre of William Elphinstone\u2019s army took place in this range in 1842 as a British force marched to Jalalabad [JUH-la-la-Bad] from Kabul. For 10 points, name this mountain range that runs through Afghanistan and northern Pakistan.", "answer": "<b><u>Hindu Kush</u></b> Mountains [or <b><u>Pariyatra Parvatra</u></b>, <b><u>Caucasus Indicus</u></b>, or <b><u>Paropamis</u><u>adae</u></b><u>; prompt</u> on <b><u>Himalaya</u></b>s <u>until \u201cthe highest po</u>i<u>nt\u201d is read]</u>  <u>[Mark Arildsen]</u>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A painting by Jacques-Louis David shows this man receiving alms while a soldier watches, astonished. Procopius recounts the lurid tale of this man being cuckolded by his adopted son Theodosius. This man's greatest victories include beating the Sassanids at Dara and the Vandals at Tricamarum [try-CAM-er-UM]. This man's first Italian campaign ended after an offer to be made emperor aroused Justinian's suspicions. For 10 points, name this Byzantine general who reconquered Italy and much of North Africa for the empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Belisarius</u> </b> [Blake Neff<u>]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "At a competition in the Soviet Union, American pianist Van Cliburn [CLYE-burn] led an acclaimed performance of this composer's <em>Piano Concerto No. 1 in B-flat minor</em>. This composer supported the eventual victors of the Serbo-Turkish War with his <em>Marche Slave</em> [Marsh slav].  Another of his pieces commemorates the Battle of Borodino by pitting the anthems \"La Marseillaise\" [Mar-SAY-ez] and \"God Save the Tsar\" against each other. For 10 points, name this composer of the <em>1812 Overture</em>.", "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich <b><u>Tchaikovsky</u></b> [or Peter Ilyich <b><u>Tchaikovsky</u></b>] [Eddie Kim]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Jamshid [Jum-SHEED] could perform this action using a cup filled with an elixir of immortality. Methods of doing this in Babylonia made use of texts like <em>Enuma Anu Enlil</em> [Ehn-U-muh AH-nu EN-leel] and entailed the practice of haruspicy [har-OO-spih-see]. This action was performed by priests of Zeus at Dodona [duh-DO-nuh]. This action was performed by augurs in Rome and could involve watching birds or reading the entrails of sheep. For 10 points, name this action that involved determining omens or predicting the future.", "answer": "<b><u>divination</u></b> [accept word forms; accept <b><u>scrying</u></b> before Enuma Anu Enlil; accept <b><u>predicting t</u><u>he future</u></b> or equivalents before mentio<u>n]</u>  <u>[Doug Graebner]</u>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This battle opened with the capture of Fort Douaumont [DOO-uh-mon] and Fort Vaux [Voh]. This battle was conceived as an effort to \u201cbleed\u201d a certain country \u201cwhite,\u201d and the defenders at this battle were resupplied by a route called \u201cthe sacred way.\u201d Erich von Falkenhayn [FALL-kun-hine] was dismissed after losing this battle, which made victorious commander Philippe Petain [Pay-TAHN] a national hero. For 10 points, name this months-long 1916 battle for a town in northeast France.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Verdun</u> </b> [Saul Hankin]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The current leader of this political party declared that he had slept with \u201cno more than 30 women\u201d in an interview with <em>GQ.</em> After allegations of a drinking problem, Charles Kennedy  stepped down as this party\u2019s leader in 2006. In 2010, this party received 23 percent of the  national vote, leading this party to form a governing coalition with David Cameron\u2019s Conservative Party. For 10 points, name this party led by Nick Clegg, a political party in the United Kingdom.", "answer": "<b><u>Liberal Democrat</u></b>s [or <b><u>Lib Dem</u></b>s]  [Dan Puma]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "According to one source, this person died fighting against the Massagetae [MASS-uh-gee-tay], led by Tomyris [Toe-my-ris], who put his head in a jar. This person won the battles of Pteria [tuh-REE-uh] and Thymbra against a rival ruler. This person\u2019s cylinder is considered by some the oldest declaration of human rights. This son of Persis overthrew his grandfather Astyages, rebelling against the Medes [mee-dees]. He was both preceded and succeeded by rulers named Cambyses. For 10 points, name this founder of the Persian Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Cyrus</u></b> the Great [or <b><u>Cyrus</u></b> II]  [Jason Zhou<u>]</u>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In this state, Robert Barnwell Rhett led the Bluffton movement, and the Fort Hill Address was delivered in this state. Events in this state inspired the coining of the phrase \"liberty and union, now and forever\" during the Webster-Hayne debate. The Force Bill allowed the president to send troops to this state. The Tariff of Abominations was attacked in an \"Exposition and Protest\" named for this state. For 10 points, name this state where the Nullification Crisis was sparked by John C. Calhoun.", "answer": "<b><u>South Carolina</u> </b> [Jordan Bro<u>wnstein]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The characters in this novel became Japanese schoolgirls in the series <em>Ikki Tousen</em>, or <em>Battle</em> <em>Vixens</em>. A video game series created by Omega Force and Koei that is based on this novel lets you kill opponents to fill your musou bar to perform special attacks, and is called <em>Dynasty</em> <em>Warriors</em>. A two-part John Woo film based on this novel was entitled <em>Red Cliff</em> after a battle in which Cao Cao [Tsao tsao] was defeated. For 10 points, name this basis for a series of twelve tactical RPG games from Koei, a Chinese classic about the battles between the states of Eastern Wu, Cao Wei, and Shu Han.", "answer": "<b><u>Romance of the Three Kingdoms</u></b> [or <b><u>Rot3k</u></b>; or <b><u>San Guo Yan Yi</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>Three King</u><u>doms</u></b><u> and</u> <b><u>San Guo</u></b>; do NOT accept \u201cRecords of the Three Kingdoms\u201d or  \u201cSanguozhi\u201d]  [Eric Mukherjee]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This theory explains the results of an 1851 experiment by Hippolyte Fizeau [EE-poh-leet FEE-zoh]. This theory can be tested by observing decay rates of muons [MEW-ons]. Lorentz transformations are used in this theory, which gives rise to the ladder and twin \u201cparadoxes\u201d thanks to length contraction and time dilation. This theory posits that the speed of light is the same in all reference frames. For 10 points, identify this theory that Albert Einstein proposed a decade before its \u201cgeneral\u201d counterpart.", "answer": "<b><u>special relativity</u></b> [or <b><u>SR</u></b>; prompt on just <b><u>relativity</u></b>, do not accept \u201cgeneral  relativity\u201d]  [Max Schindler]", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "David Beatty drew one fleet north during this battle, which resulted in a crossing of the T. The flagship of one side of this battle, the <em>Iron Duke</em>, heavily damaged the <em>SMS Konig</em>. During this battle, Admiral John Jellicoe achieved a strategic victory but suffered a tactical loss against the High Seas Fleet under Reinhard Scheer [sheer]. For 10 points, name this battle that took place off of the Denmark coast, the largest naval battle of World War I.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Jutland</u></b> [pronounced \u201cyoot-land\u201d, but accept pronunciations as written]  Following t<u>he creat</u>ion of the <em>HMS Dreadnought</em>, the Royal Navy built what type of large ships such as the <em>HMS Invincible</em> that were much quicker than battleships but vulnerable due to their light armor? ANSWER: <b><u>battle cruisers</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>cruiser</u></b>s]  [Eric Dougl<u>ass]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This event was the subject of investigations by Admiral Rickover and the Sampson Board. The entity at the center of this event was commanded by Charles Sigsbee, and Joseph Pulitzer edited articles about this event in one of the first examples of Yellow Journalism. For 10 points, name this 1898 event in which a coal explosion may have led to the explosion of a United States sea vessel in Havana Harbor.", "answer": "<b><u>sinking</u> </b>of the <b><u>USS Maine</u></b> [or <b><u>explosion</u></b> of the <b><u>USS Maine</u></b> or equivalents mentioning <b><u>bombin</u><u>gs</u></b> or <b><u>mines</u></b><u>]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A canopy designed by this artist is composed of four Solomonic columns adorned with bees, a symbol of the Barberini family. His two sets of \u201csemicircular colonnades lead up to St. Peter\u2019s Basilica, also featuring his <em>Baldacchino</em> [BAL-duh-\u201ckey\u201d-no]. Light shines as an angel pierces the title woman with an arrow in his best known work. For 10 points, name this Baroque [buh-ROAK] sculptor of <em>The Ecstasy of St. Theresa</em>.", "answer": "Gian Lorenzo <b><u>Bernini</u> </b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "The Persian-dictated \u201cKing\u2019s Peace\u201d brought an end to one war named for this city, which the general Lucius Mummius sacked in 146 BC. Ships could be moved across the massive <em>diolkos</em> [dee-OL-kos] ramp constructed by this city\u2019s tyrant Periander. This city named the third primary order of Greek architecture, along with the Doric and Ionic orders. For 10 points, name this Greek city located on a namesake isthmus in the Peloponnesus.", "answer": "<b><u>Corinth</u></b> [or <b><u>Korinthos</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "A military junta in this nation fought against the Montoneros and committed the Trelew [truh-LEW] massacre as part of its Process of National Reorganization, actions protested against by the mothers of the Plaza del Mayo. Admiral Jorge Anaya also pushed the junta into a war to redirect internal discontent in this nation. For 10 points, identify this nation where many people disappeared as a result of the Dirty War.", "answer": "<b><u>Argentina</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The rise of these places is detailed in Kenneth T. Jackson\u2019s <em>Crabgrass Frontier</em>. Victor Gruen attempted to create pedestrian spaces in these areas by designing both outdoor and indoor shopping malls. These places grew in the mid-20th century due to white flight and the GI Bill offering low-interest home loans. For 10 points, name these primarily residential low-density areas that are located outside of major cities.", "answer": "<b><u>suburb</u></b>s", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "Using Brownian motion, the value of a quantity named for this man was determined by Jean Perrin [Puh-RIN]. This man formulated a law stating that the volume of a gas is proportional to the number of particles, which, along with the combined gas law, yields the ideal gas law. For 10 points, name this Italian scientist who lends his name to the number of entities in a mole.", "answer": "Amedeo <b><u>Avogadro</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "02 times 10 raised to what integer power?", "answer": "the <b><u>23</u></b>rd power  [Max Schindler<u>]</u>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "In 1900, this state's governor William Goebel [Go-BELL] became the only sitting governor in U.S. history to be assassinated. Andrew Jackson used a campaign song that referred to \"the hunters of\" this state. After initially declaring neutrality in the Civil War, this state eventually stayed with the Union. For 10 points, name this state, the birthplace of Jefferson Davis and Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "<b><u>Kentucky</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This man used the name of his supervisor, Thomas A. Scott, to issue an order to burn a</u></b> <b><u>gro</u><u>up of wrecked railroad cars blocking the Pennsylvania Railroad. A company founded</u></b> <b><u>by this man built the Eads Bridge in St. Louis. This man, who owned the (+)</u><u> Keystone</u> <u>Bridge Company, left Henry Clay Frick with the task of handling the (*)</u></b><u> Ho</u>mestead Strike.  This author of the article \"The Gospel of Wealth\" merged his namesake company with two others to form U.S. Steel. For 10 points, name this Scotland-born steel magnate and philanthropist.", "answer": "Andrew <b><u>Carnegie</u> </b> [Kenji Golimlim]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Supporters of this team are known as \u201cKopites\u201d [CO-pites] and sing along to Gerry and</u></b> <b><u>the</u><u> Pacemakers\u2019 cover of \u201cYou\u2019ll Never Walk Alone.\u201d 96 of its fans lost their lives in the</u></b> <b><u>Hillsborough Disaster and are the subject of a memorial outside</u><u> (+) Anfield. This team</u> <u>contests the Merseyside Derby with Everton and have won the E</u>nglish First Division 18 (*) </b>times. Last summer, they signed Mario Balotelli to help replace the departing Luis Suarez. For 10 points, name this soccer team managed by Brendan Rodgers and captained by Steven Gerrard.", "answer": "<b><u>Liverpool</u></b> Football Club [prompt on \u201cthe Reds\u201d]  [Dennis Lo<u>o]</u>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>This scientist postulated that the deficiency in color perception among the color-blind is</u></b> <b><u>du</u><u>e to a discoloration of the liquid medium of the eyeball. This man was the first to show</u></b> <b><u>that the</u><u> (+) pressure of a mixture of gases is equal to the sum of its components\u2019 partial</u> <u>pressur</u>es. A mass unit named for this man is equal to (*)</b> one-twelfth the weight of a neutral atom of carbon, exactly one amu. For 10 points, name this English chemist who developed the law of multiple proportions, a component of his modern atomic theory.", "answer": "John <b><u>Dalton</u> </b> [Sriram Pendyala<u>]</u>", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "<b><u>The first metal movable type book was printed in this region, which once used a bone</u></b> <b><u>ran</u><u>k system. A polity in this region was victorious at the battle of (+)</u><u> Salsu River. A</u> <u>kingdom here successfully resisted a Khitan invasion, while a later p</u>olity won a decisive victory at Noryang Point through the use of (*)</b> turtle ships. Sejong the Great is credited with inventing a widely used alphabet in this region, which became a vassal state under Mongol rule before regaining independence under Joseon rule. For 10 points, name this peninsular home of the Goguryeo and Silla dynasties.", "answer": "<b><u>Korea</u> </b> [Zihan Zhen<u>g]</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Eight members of the Contarini family held this title. People who held this title would</u></b> <b><u>bo</u><u>ard a bucentaur and throw a ring into the sea as part of a symbolic \"marriage\"</u></b> <b><u>ceremony. That ceremony celebrates the day a holder of this title conquered Dalm</u><u>atia,</u></b> <b><u>known as (+)</u><u> Ascension Day. Ludovico Manin was the last person with this title, whose</u></b> <b><u>holders lived</u> in a palace connected to St. (*) </b>Mark's Basilica and controlled a certain \"Most Serene Republic.\" For 10 points, identify this title held by leaders of a city-state on the Adriatic Sea.", "answer": "<b><u>Doge of Venice</u></b> [prompt on partial answer]  [Kenji Goli<u>mlim]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A future holder of this position declared that \u201cGinger Rodgers did everything Fred</u></b>  <b><u>Astaire did, just backwards in high heels\u201d and said that another politician was \u201cborn with</u></b>  <b><u>a silver foot in his mouth\u201d during her keynote speech at the</u> (+)1988 DNC. Another <u>governor of this state faced controversy over the implement</u>ation of the InnerChange Program and the (*)</b> execution of Karla Faye Tucker. That man defeated Ann Richards for this post and vacated this position after beating Al Gore in the presidential election of 2000. For 10 points, name this position held in the 1990s by George W. Bush.", "answer": "<b><u>Texas Governor</u></b> [or <b><u>Governor of Texas</u></b>]  [Puma]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>William Apess helped organize the successful Mashpee revolt against this state, and</u></b> <b><u>set</u><u>tlers from this state launched an expedition against the sachem Sassacus. The Treat</u><u>y of</u></b> <b><u>Casco Bay ended another conflict in this state, in which one side was led by the son of</u><u> (+)</u> <u>Massasoit. Edmund Andros served as a governor in this state, which fought the Pequ</u>ot War and crushed the Wampanoag in (*)</b> King Philip\u2019s War. Myles Standish committed several massacres as military commander here. For 10 points, name this state in which the Patuxet Squanto saved the colonists arriving in the <em>Mayflower</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Massachusetts</u> </b> [Zihan Zhen<u>g]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man examined the long-term effects of military socialization on soldiers in his</u></b> <b><u>re</u><u>cently developed \"social intensity syndrome.\" This man attempted to explain how</u> <u>good</u></b> <b><u>people have the capacity to do evil in his book</u> </b><em><b><u>The</u></b></em> <b><u>(+)</u></b><em><b><u>Lucifer Effect</u></b></em><b><u>. A 1971 experiment</u> <u>conducted by this man was funded by the US Offi</u>ce of Naval Research and included the exceptionally brutal (*)</b> \"John Wayne.\" That experiment placed a divided group of students in a simulated jail for 6 days. For 10 points, name this psychologist who conducted the Stanford Prison Experiment.", "answer": "Philip <b><u>Zimbardo</u></b> [or Philip George <b><u>Zimbardo</u></b>]  [Chris Manners]", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}], "bonuses": []}